Guide to the Pauline Bart papers, 1925-2008 and undated, bulk 1969-1995 RL.10069
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pauline Bart papers
1925-2008 and undated, bulk 1969-1995
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bart, Pauline
RL.10069
45 Linear Feet 91 boxes
Pauline Bart is a feminist sociologist and former professor of sociology and psychiatry. From the 1960s to the 1990s, Bart was active in many feminist and civil rights issues, including anti-pornography protests, sexual assault and rape law reform, Jewish and middle-aged women's advocacy, reproductive rights, and violence against women. The Pauline Bart papers consists of personal files, including correspondence, appointment books, diaries, peer-reviewed mansucripts for which Bart served as a referee, subject files for conferences Bart attended, and other material related to Bart's personal and professional life; drafts and published copies of articles, papers, and reviews written by Bart; papers related to classes taught by Bart at the University of Illinois in Chicago, the University of California at Los Angeles, and other institutions; and research files, including interview transcripts and other papers related to the Jane Collective, transcripts of interviews with 94 survivors of sexual assault or attempted rape and other papers related to Bart's study of rape avoidance; interview transcripts and other papers related to a study of depression, and other research files on topics such as pornography, depression, violence against women, the Illinois sexual assault statute, feminism, rape, and homosexuality.
Historical note
Pauline Bart is a feminist sociologist and former professor of sociology and psychiatry. From the 1960s to the 1990s, Bart was active in many feminist and civil rights issues, including anti-pornography protests, sexual assault and rape law reform, Jewish and middle-aged women's advocacy, reproductive rights, and violence against women.
Bart received her Ph.D. in sociology from the University of California at Los Angeles in 1967. After struggling to find a long-term position for several years, she became a professor at the University of Illinois in Chicago, where she remained from 1970-1992. Bart experienced a turbulent relationship with UIC administrators throughout her time there, and as she rose through the ranks of professorship to achieve tenure, she struggled to attain salary equity with her male counterparts. In 1992, Bart was implicated in a controversy involving one of her male students, Donald Dixon, who accused Bart of making discriminatory remarks against men and characterizing him in racist and sexist terms to his fellow classmates. Although Bart denied these allegations, her classes were reassigned and her relationship with the University of Illinois at Chicago ended over the matter. Bart then served as a lecturer at the University of California at Los Angeles before retiring in 1995. She currently lives in Morrisville, North Carolina.
Access Restrictions
Boxes 35-39 and 90-91 are closed to researchers until 2039.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The Pauline Bart papers are arranged into four series. The Personal Files Series contains correspondence, appointment books, diaries, peer-reviewed mansucripts for which Bart served as a referee, and other material related to Bart's personal and professional life, including papers related to her struggles to achieve salary equity and documentation of the 1992 controversy which led to her termination from the University of Illinois at Chicago. Also included in this series are subject files for conferences Bart attended to present papers or serve on panels. The Writings Series contains drafts and copies of reviews, written by Bart, of articles and books published by various authors; drafts of Bart's book, Stopping Rape: Successful Survival Strategies, and other papers related to the book's publication; drafts and published copies of articles and academic papers written by Bart; and other materials related to her writings, including book contracts, reprint requests, and reviews of her work. The Teaching Materials Series contains papers related to classes taught by Bart at the University of Illinois in Chicago, the University of California at Los Angeles, and other institutions. Materials include syllabi, lists and copies of course readings, student papers, and other papers. The Research Files Series contains interview transcripts, content analysis, and other papers related to the Jane Collective, which Bart researched in pursuit of her article "Seizing the Means of Reproduction: An Illegal Feminist Abortion Collective - How and Why it Worked;" materials related to Stopping Rape: Successful Survival Strategies, including transcripts of interviews with 94 survivors of sexual assault or attempted rape, notebooks containing content analysis of the interviews, grant applications and drafts, Viva rape questionnaires, and other papers; interview transcripts and other papers related to a study of depression; and other research files on topics such as pornography, depression, violence against women, the Illinois sexual assault statute, feminism, rape, and homosexuality. The Audiotapes series contains recordings of talks given by Bart, conference sessions, presentations, interviews, and classes conducted at the University of Illinois at Chicago. Also included are recordings of 9 interviews with members of the Jane Collective (see box 90).
Provenance
The Pauline Bart papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in August 2009.
Arrangement
Materials in the Personal Files Series are arranged alphabetically by folder title, with the exception of the Correspondence and Notebooks and Diaries Subseries, which are arranged chronologically. Materials in the Writings, Teaching Materials, and Research Files Series are arranged alphabetically by folder title, with the exception of the Other Research Files Subseries, which is arranged alphabetically by subject. Original folder titles have, for the most part, been retained.
Some original documents may have been replaced by redacted photocopies to protect personally identifying information.
Related Materials
Phyllis Chesler Papers, 1968-1990 (Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Merle Hoffman Papers, circa 1944-2012 and undated, bulk 1961-2000 (Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Feminism -- Psychological aspects.; Feminism and higher education -- United States.; Wages -- Sex differences -- United States.; Abortion -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Abortion services -- United States -- History; Jewish women -- United States.; Rape -- Prevention.; Rape -- Illinois -- Chicago -- Case studies.; Women psychologists.; Jane (Abortion service); Rape victims.; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Rape -- United States -- Prevention.; Rape -- Psychological aspects.; Feminism and education -- United States; Homosexuality.; Pornography -- Social aspects -- United States.; Lesbianism -- United States; Abortion counseling -- United States; Dworkin, Andrea; Scully, Diana; MacKinnon, Catharine A.; Grossman, Marlyn; Chesler, Phyllis
- Personal Files Series, 1925-2008; undated
  Scope and Contents
  The Personal Files Series contains correspondence, appointment books, diaries, peer-reviewed mansucripts for which Bart served as a referee, and other material related to Bart's personal and professional life, including papers related to her struggles to achieve salary equity and documentation of the 1992 controversy which led to her termination from the University of Illinois at Chicago.
  - Correspondence Subseries, 1960-2008; undated
    The Correspondence Subseries includes Bart's personal and professional correspondence. Much of the correspondence relates to Bart's plans to travel to conferences or universities to lecture about her research. There are also letters from sociologists, professors, and other scholars requesting copies of Bart's writings or more information on her research. There is very little family correspondence.
    While most of the correspondence in this subseries is professional in nature, personal correspondence reflects the turbulent relationships among members of the feminist movement throughout the second half of the 20th century. As the movement expanded, feminists often disagreed with each other on various issues, and these disagreements can be seen in several volatile exchanges in this subseries, in which Bart was either directly or tangentially involved. Some of Bart's more frequent correspondents include feminists such as Catherine MacKinnon, Andrea Dworkin, and Phyllis Chelser.
    Particularly in the late 1980s and early 1990s, Bart struggled with her own feminist identity, and she felt as though feminism was generally becoming more conservative while she was becoming more radical. During this time, Bart also struggled with her feelings regarding her own sexuality and her relationships with women, depression, and thoughts of suicide, all of which are reflected in her personal correspondence.
    - 1960-1974, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1975-1977, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1978-1983, 7 folders (Box 3)
    - 1984-1990, 7 folders (Box 4)
    - 1991-2008, undated; 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Notebooks and Diaries Subseries, 1941-2007; undated
    The Notebooks and Diaries Subseries contains Bart's address book, appointment books, autograph albums, diaries, and a notebook. The two autograph albums in this subseries were compiled during Bart's time at P.S. 235 and Winthrop Junior High School in Brooklyn, New York. Bart kept diaries regularly from childhood throughout her adult life. The diaries' contents are often varied and irregular, including dated entries as well as notes from presentation, phone numbers, and reminders. Bart frequently recorded her dreams.
    - Address Book, undated; 1 folders (Box 6)
    - Appointment Books
      - April 1975, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - May 1975, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - 1982, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - January 1991-June 1992, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - July 1992-February 1993, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - November 1995, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - 1995, 1 folders (Box 6)
      - 1998, 1 folders (Box 7)
      - 1999, 1 folders (Box 7)
      - 2000, 1 folders (Box 7)
      - July-August 2005, 1 folders (Box 7)
    - Autograph Album, 1941; 1 folders (Box 8)
    - Autograph Album, 1944; 1 folders (Box 8)
    - Diaries
      - 1944-1946, 1 folders (Box 8)
      - 1972, 1 folders (Box 8)
      - 1974, 1 folders (Box 8)
      - 1978-1979, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - 1981, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - circa 1981, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - circa 1981-1982, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - 1982-1983, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - 1984, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - circa 1984, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - 1987, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - 1988, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - 1989, 1 folders (Box 9)
      - circa 1989, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1991, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1992, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1993, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1994, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - circa 1994, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1995, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - circa 1996-1997, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1998, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - circa 1998, 1 folders (Box 10)
      - 1998-1999, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - 1999, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - 1999-2000, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - circa 2000, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - 2002-2003, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - 2004-2005, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - 2004-2007, 1 folders (Box 11)
      - undated, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Notebook, undated; 1 folders (Box 12)
  - Refereed Manuscripts Subseries, 1975-1986
    The Refereed Manuscripts Subseries contains copies of articles for which Bart served as a peer reviewer, review sheets containing her comments on these manuscripts, and occasional correspondence with journal editors.
    - ASR Rape Paper, 1979; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Gender and Society, 1986; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Letters of Recommendation/Referee, 1979-1981; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Psychology of Women Quarterly, 1975-1979; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Sex Roles, 1975 June; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Social Problems, 1976; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Women and Health, 1977-1978; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1981; 1 folders (Box 13)
  - Conferences Subseries, 1969-1995; undated
    The Conferences Subseries contains subject files for conferences that Bart attended, either as a speaker or as a regular attendee. In cases where Bart traveled to a conference to present a paper, drafts of these papers may be included. Frequently attended conferences include the annual meetings of the American Sociological Association (ASA), National Women's Studies Association (NWSA), Child Sexual Assault Services Network (CSASN), Society for the Study of Social Problems (SSSP), and Sociologists for Women in Society.
    - Aggression Conference, 1986; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - American Association of University Women, Naperville, 1974; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - ASA Caucus, 1969-1972; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - ASA papers, 1972; 1978; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - Transcript- ASA meeting, A. Rossi section 9/6/77, 1977; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - ASA Boston, 1979; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - ASA Committee on meeting sites, 1979; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - ASA Council, 1979; 1 folders (Box 13)
    - ASA 1979 Council, 2nd Meeting Jan. 13-14, Washington D.C., 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA 1979 Council Meeting March 10-11, 1979, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA Council June 15-16, 1979, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA related materials, 1979; 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA to take and other things, 1979; 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA 1980 Council Sept. 1-2, 1979, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - 1980 ASA Council March 15-16, 1980, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - 1980 ASA Council August 29, 1980, 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA meetings, 1980; 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA, 1987; 1 folders (Box 14)
    - ASA meeting notes, 1988; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - ASA, 1990; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - sex and gender section ASA meeting, 1990; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - ASA, 1991; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - ASA, 1993; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - American Sociological Asso., undated; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Association for Women in Psychology National Conference, 1986; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Third Berkshire Conference on the History of Women, 1976; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Chicago Lying-In Hospital Women in Conflict Symposium, 1976; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Chicago Conference on Bisexual Behavior, 1973; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - CSASN meetings, 1988; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - CSASN documents, 1990; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - CSASN: sexual assault- the adolescent victim, 1990; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Citizen Exchange Council conference May 20-June 1, 1991, 1 folders (Box 15)
    - 26th annual conference on aging, 1973; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - East Coast Conference of Socialist Sociologists, undated; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Educational Task Force on Pornography lecture, Indiana University, March 1988, 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Feminist Perspectives on Law conference, London, 1986; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Fort Wayne November 1978, 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Fourth International Interdisciplinary Congress on Women, 1990; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Gainesville Women in Health April 1-4 1976, 1 folders (Box 15)
    - gerontology meetings Oct 29 8:30-10:15, 1974; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Groves Conference on Marriage and the Family, 1974; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Groves, 1975; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Philly HEW conference on women and health, 1976; 1 folders (Box 15)
    - Hobart and William Smith Conference, 1974; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Institute of Legal Studies Madison, 1987; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - International Congress on Rape, Israel, 1986; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - ISA world congress, 1990; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Merrill-Palmer Institute, 1975; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Michigan Speech 10/7/87, 1987; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Midwest Sociological Meetings, 1974-1975; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Midwest Sociological Meeting, 1988; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Mundelein, 1979; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - National Association of Women's Centers convention, 1986; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - National Council of Jewish Women conference 21 January 1974, 1 folders (Box 16)
    - NCASA, 1988; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - NOW Park Ridge-Des Plaines Talk 3/11/93, 1993; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - NWSA, 1986; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - NWSA, 1990; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - NWSA conference, 1993; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - NWSA, 1995; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - National Conference on Women and the Law, 1986; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - New Understandings? Experience of Women 1992 Illinois College 9/21-25, 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Northeastern, 1975; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Oshkosh Conference, 1972; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Pacific Meetings, 1973; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Portugal December 1988, 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Psychology of Women: Issues for the Seventies, 1975; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Psychosomatic Gynecology, 1974; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Public Affairs Committee Chicago, 1989; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Public Affairs Committee May 21, 1990, 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Radcliffe conference roster, 1972; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - Rape Law Seminar Northwestern University, 1994; 1 folders (Box 16)
    - San Diego Feb 14 Rape, 1976; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Santa Clara Psychology of Women, 1977; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Society for the Reform of Criminal Law conference Australia, 1989; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SSSS Nov. 1-3 Las Vegas, 1974; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SSSP, 1975; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Society for the Study of Social Problems, 1979; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SSSP, 1980; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS, 1977; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS Cleveland, 1978; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS Milwaukee, 1978; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - "Woman-Identified Woman: What It Means" (SWS Annual Meeting, 1978), 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS, 1978-1979; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS, 1979; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS Reps and ISA sex roles, 1979; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS sex issues, 1979; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - SWS, 1980; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Speech, Equality, and Harm Conference Chicago, 1993; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Third International Interdisciplinary Congress on Women, Dublin, Ireland, 1987; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - University of Chicago Symposium on Academic Feminism, 1987; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - University of Illinois Conference on Feminist Scholarship, 1978; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - UIC Conference on Women and Gender 4/16/93, 1993; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Lecture at University of Iowa, 1974; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Pornography/Prostitution Conference, U Mich Ann Arbor 10/30-31/92, 1 folders (Box 17)
    - West Virginia University September Festival of Women, 1978; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - 2nd Annual Western Regional Conference on Sexual Assault Salt Lake 5/28-30/77, 1977; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Women and Health Care Symposium, 1974; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Working Conference on Issues Pertaining to Sexual Assault Ann Arbor 5/25-27/77, 1977; 1 folders (Box 17)
    - Loose conference materials, 1970-1995; 1 folders (Box 17)
  - Other Personal Files Subseries, 1925-2000; undated
    The Other Personal Files Subseries contains Bart's personal files, including certificates, clippings and interviews featuring Bart, copies of leases, and other files. There is also a very minimal amount of information on Bart's family. This subseries contains material related to Bart's struggles to achieve salary equity and documentation of the 1992 controversy which led to her termination from the University of Illinois at Chicago.
    - Alumni College in Tuscany certificate, 2000; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Application materials for visiting professor, 1981; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - ASA referendum, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Bart Clippings/Interviews, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Curriculum Vitae and related materials, 1976-1995; undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - CWLU, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Department of Psychology meetings, 1991; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Department of Psychology transfer, 1989; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Dissertation copy, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Dr. Bart ER, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - England and Germany fall 1992, 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Eulogy for Manya Prozanskaya Lackow, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Every Other Weekly interview with Pauline Bart, 1970; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Firing from University of Illinois at Chicago, 1992; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Funding for Travel, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Grad School UCLA exams, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Guggenheim Foundation referral, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Jobs, 1988-1990; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - JSI uproar, 1980; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Linda Frankel, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Madison, undated; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Marriage certificate, 1949; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Marriage certificate- Mildred Prozan and Emil Lackow, 1925; 1 folders (Box 18)
    - Members JWAA, 1974; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Mujeres Latinas Unidas, 1994; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Office rental info: lease, correspondence, etc., 1977; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Photographs of unidentified house, 1972; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Professorship, 1981; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Recommendations, 1986-1987; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Revised agreements on lease till August 1979, 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Santa Barbara, 1981; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Schenkman Publishing Company, 1973; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - State legislature award, 1990; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Transaction, Incorporated, 1978; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - UCLA Job, 1994-1995; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - University of Illinois Salary Struggle, 1974-1990; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - University of Illinois 1992 re: tenure and classes, 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Urban Art Retreat, 1993; 1 folders (Box 19)
    - Loose personal papers, 1973-1995; undated; 1 folders (Box 19)
- Writings Series, 1963-2005; undated
  The Writings Series contains drafts and copies of reviews, written by Bart, of articles and books published by various authors; drafts of Bart's book, Stopping Rape: Successful Survival Strategies, and other papers related to the book's publication; drafts and published copies of articles and academic papers written by Bart; and other materials related to her writings, including book contracts, reprint requests, and reviews of her work.
  - Reviews Subseries, 1973-1993; undated
    The reviews subseries contains both drafts and published copies of reviews written by Bart. Reviews tend to cover articles related to women's studies, feminism, and sociology.
    - The Chicago Maternity Center Story, undated; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - Chodorow review oob, 1993; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - The Curse: A Cultural History of Menstruation by Janice Delaney, 1977; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - Daly, Mary: Gyn/ecology- Review of chapter on femail friendship, undated; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - The Depressed Woman, 1974; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - Female Orgasm Fisher, 1973; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - Feminism Unmodified, 1989; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - In Necessity and Sorrow, 1976; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - Legal Kidnapping, 1977; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - Lives in Stress, 1982; 1 folders (Box 20)
    - The Mermaid and the Minotaur, 1977; 1 folders (Box 20)